<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<quilts>
    <story>
        <title>Sally Jones - 1913</title>
        <anchor>1</anchor>
        <type>marriage</type>
        <patterns>dresden plate, village green, pot of flowers, lone star, ocean wave, nine diamonds, bowtie</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>As a child in the 1910’s, Sally spent a lot of time “dabbling around in the rag bag” looking for fabric scraps to make doll clothes from. Although she sometimes failed to get anything made, for Sally, the fun was in trying.</p>
                
                <p>When she was 17, Sally began working for a woman who was a prolific quilter. She developed an interest in the craft, and with the help of her boss, pieced her first quilt in the star pattern. Sally continued making quilts through the 1930s because she was “looking forward to getting married someday, and [she] had to have quilts.” At the beginning of a new marriage, it was important for a household to have a few quilts to start out with, to keep newlyweds warm through winter and to insulate forthcoming children in the first years of their lives.</p>
                
               <p> Sally did marry in 1937, and she had five new quilts to start out with, including the first quilt she made independently, in the ocean wave pattern. Sally continued to make many quilts over her lifetime for her family to use. She also sometimes made quilts as special gifts; she remembers making a nine-diamonds quilt for her nephew when he married, and a bowtie quilt for her nice when she married. When quilting for other people, Sally notes that she was always more careful with her stitches than when she was just making “common quilts” for herself. </p>
                
                <p>Sally often attended quilting bees where she remembers using the fan-pattern for quilting, and sometimes quilting by the piece, wherein you simply quilt around each square. Sally always enjoyed the discussion that took place at quilting bees, especially when “the girls would get to talking about when they were young… I always loved to hear when they talked about their courting days.”</p>
                
               <p> When asked about the personal significance that quilts have for her and her family, Sally recalls an anecdote about her mother and father. Sally’s mother was also a prolific quilter, although she often made quilts exclusively from scrap material. Sally’s mother made a scrap quilt “on the order of a nine diamonds” towards the end of her life, which she gave to her husband by lying it over him in bed one night and saying “I want you to have that.” Later, after her mother died, Sally’s father went to live with her sister and took the quilt with him, keeping it with him until the very end of his life.</p>
        </description>

    </story>

    <story>
        <title>Mary Smith - 1897</title>
        <anchor>2</anchor>
        <type>craft</type>
        <patterns>trip around the world, flower pattern, sunbonnet sue</patterns>
        <description><p>Mary was born in 1897 and married in 1915. She had five children. Early in her marriage, Mary helped her mother in law make a quilt in the trip around the world pattern.</p>
            
           <p> The first quilt Mary made by herself was a heavy quilt constructed from old woolens and tacked together, which she and her husband used to keep warm as newlyweds in their drafty farm house. However, because she often helped her husband out in the fields (“just as a man would”), Mary didn’t begin making a lot of quilts until after her husband died and she learned to quilt (instead of tack) quilts by watching her friends. Even then, she never bought fabric to make quilts; she always used scraps. According to Mary, you shouldn’t mix new and old material, and you shouldn’t use new material to patch a quilt.</p>
            
           <p> Mary does not remember attending any quilting bees as a young woman, although sometimes ladies from her church would “get together at someone’s house to quilt a quilt for a needy person.” Instead, she remembers many community apple-peelings and corn shuckings, in which neighbors would help one another process food for preservation. According to Mary, there is a real art to peeling an apple without removing all the fruit. She says, “I believe there’s an art in everything we do, isn’t there?”</p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Ida Johnson - 1899</title>
        <anchor>3</anchor>
        <type>home</type>
        <patterns>wedding ring, odd fellar, nine diamonds, wedding ring</patterns>
        <description><p>Ida’s mother first taught her to quilt when she was 13 years old. According to Ida, her mother “would never have a machine stitch on a quilt”—she exclusively pieced and quilted by hand. If she needed them, Ida’s mother might make 2-3 quilts a year. Ida remembers that when she was 14, she carried bread and eggs to the grocery store for her neighbor, for which she was paid a nickel. She saved all her nickels until she had 35 cents, and then her mother used that money to buy enough fabric to make her a dress. Some of the fabric scraps from this dress were later integrated into her mother’s quilts.</p>
            
            <p> As an adult woman, Ida began making crazy quilts as a way of using up scraps of fabric that wouldn’t be used any other way. Later, she began to get pattern ideas from her neighbors. Ida used sheep’s wool as batting in her quilts so that they would keep you warm in unheated houses. Quilts were much heavier than blankets; Ida recalls that you “couldn’t get a heavy blanket, a real good warm blanket,” and quilts were the only way to keep warm. In the last few years she quilted, Ida held quilting parties where she would invite neighbor women over to quilt a pieced quilt, and all she'd have to do was "fix them a good lunch.”</p> 
            
            <p> Ida married her first husband in 1919. He was a farmer, and was a “big fan of orchards” and a skilled grafter. They had 48 apple trees that he maintained and one tree with seven different kinds of apples on it! Ida recalls the difficulty of their lives, noting the effort and skill required to make soap and do laundry, and says, “There was a lot of hard work to anything you done back then.”</p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Susan Presley - 1910</title>
        <anchor>4</anchor>
        <type>love</type>
        <patterns></patterns>
        <description><p>
            Susan was the third youngest child of twelve, although she notes that only 10 of her brothers and sisters survived to adulthood. During her childhood, Susan remembers her mother drying food, like apples, peaches, corn, and pumpkins, because her family did not have enough money to buy canned goods. Her mother also raised chickens, and cows for milk, which she churned into butter and sold at the “little country store” in order to buy dry goods the family needed. Susan’s mother did make some quilts from old pairs of pants, but she also wove and spun yarn extensively, sometimes selling her woven fabrics to other people.</p>
            
           <p> Susan’s husband was a farmer, and they lived on a farm where they raised “most everything they ate.” Susan started to quilt when she was 14 and followed in her mother’s footsteps, making quilts from “whatever material I’ve got.” The first quilt Susan made was in the butterfly pattern, which someone gave to her and she “just thought it was pretty.” Susan sometimes bought fabric for quilts, and sometimes other people gave her their scarps.</p>
            
           <p> Susan remembers that, throughout her life, when people were sick or having hard times, neighbors would bring them quilts, food, and clothes. She believes that people stopped having quilting bees when "all the love drifted out” of communities.
        </p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Martha Daniels - 1905</title>
        <anchor>5</anchor>
        <type>family</type>
        <patterns>wedding ring, lone star, string, nine diamonds</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>
                Martha was born in 1905. When she was a child, Martha’s mother knit and spun yarn, caned chair seats, and quilted. Martha remembers that her mother "would knit daddy socks all the time.” Martha married in 1922, at the age of 16, and had 12 children, although, she notes with sadness, that she gave birth to a set of twins who later contracted whooping cough and died at 15 months.</p>
                
                <p>Martha learned to quilt from her mother, and now gets ideas for her own quilt patterns by looking at her mother’s quilts and scrap pieces. Although she sometimes uses the sewing machine to piece, Martha would never use it to quilt. When her daughters got married, Martha made each of them a quilt to begin their new households with. Like her mother, she also makes quilts to give to people whose houses have burned down.
            </p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Joan Beavers - 1912</title>
        <anchor>6</anchor>
        <type>love</type>
        <patterns>log cabin, lone star, strawberry quilt, dutch boy, dutch girl, small basket</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>
                Joan was born in 1912 in Dickenson county, Virginia. Both of her parents were born in log cabins. Her mother was a prolific quilter, making tacked quilts from linsey material (which has a linen warp and a woolen weft), as well as cotton and percale. Joan also remembers a special quilt made from velvet, which was used on the top of the bed (instead of under a more formal comforter).</p>
                
                <p>Joan’s father was killed in a mine when she was 7, and as a result, she married when she was 14 “because she wanted to get help for mother.” Although at the time she thought she was just getting married to help her mother, but looking back, she believes she did always love her husband. This feeling was magnified especially after his passing.</p>
                
               <p> Joan taught herself to quilt and made mostly comforters because she did not know how to piece quilt tops. Now Joan mostly quilts so she has something to do in wintertime. When asked about the significance of quilts in her life, Joan says, “You know there’s a meaning for everything, isn’t there?”</p>
                
             <p>   During her married years, Joan remembers that neighbors often came to check on one another. She says she and her friends held lots of quilting bees and that everyone’s husbands would also come along to help in the tobacco barn. Neighbors might have quiltings during the day, and then come back at night for dances “and square dance all night.” According to Joan, “That was before all the love went away. They loved each other then.”</p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Betsy Hart - 1903</title>
        <anchor>7</anchor>
        <type>family</type>
        <patterns>fools puzzle, lone star, wedding ring, flower garden, dove in the window, whig rose, colonial girl, dutch boy dogwoood, fools puzzle, maple leaf</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>Betsy was born in 1903 to a farming family. Growing up, Betsy’s father grew much of the food for their family—she remembers that he even grew his own wheat. When her mother was married, a friend suggested that she try to make two new quilts every winter. There were nine people in Betsy’s family, and her mother had to make enough quilts for each of their beds.</p>
                
              <p>  When Betsy’s mother got old, she began to quilt all the time because it was something to do while she sat during the day. Eventually Betsy’s mother had to have her thumb removed, which limited her to making pieced quilt tops on the sewing machine. It was here, piecing quilts at the sewing machine, that Betsy’s mother eventually had a heart attack and died.</p>
                
               <p> Betsy learned to quilt mostly by helping her mother—she says the craft was “handed down.” She made her fist quilt in the nine diamonds pattern when she was 16. Her mother guided her through this process in a way that was subtle and respectful of Betsy’s own ideas. However, due to the large stitches Betsy used, this quilt eventually fell apart. </p>
                
               <p> Betsy married in 1925. Her husband was a carpenter and together they had four children and raised two. Before her marriage, Betsy’s mother gave her two woolen quilts filled with wool from her sister’s sheep. Although she did not quilt a lot when her children were young, Betsy eventually got into making “fancy quilts” with appliqué, in addition to crocheting and tatting. </p>
                
                <p>Betsy recalls lots of quilting bees. In her mother’s time, "You didn't have to invite people--if they knew you were quilting, they'd just come.” After her husband died, Betsy remembers a young mother from her neighborhood who wanted to learn to quilt. Betsy helped her and a few other young women, and eventually formed a quilting circle with the young mothers and some of the other “old ladies from the neighborhood.” Betsy says that all of the women would laugh and have a good time, and that “It’s just something i guess—its like I said, we get together—the togetherness, you know i think the friendship means a lot."</p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Cathy James - 1907</title>
        <anchor>8</anchor>
        <type>marriage</type>
        <patterns>string quilts, nine diamonds, wedding ring, chariot wheel, dresden plate, dutch doll, lone star</patterns>
        <description><p>
            Cathy made her first quilt when she was 15 and newly married. Her mother taught her how to piece the quilt in the nine diamond pattern from two old dresses. Growing up, Cathy’s mother made a money by quilting quilts for other people. Cathy also learned to sew by watching her sister-in-law, who was a seamstress. </p>
            
           <p> While making quilts for her family, Cathy often used scraps from children’s clothing. After Cathy’s husband died, women from the Bible circle at her church would come and help her quilt. One of these women also used to come bring her food and “just eat” with her. These friendships helped a lot with Cathy’s depression following the death of her husband.
        </p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Elizabeth Morris - 1902</title>
        <anchor>9</anchor>
        <type>home</type>
        <patterns>sugar bowl, trip around the world, strip quilt, log cabin, dove at the window, crazy quilt, nine diamonds</patterns>
        <description><p>
            Elizabeth’s grandmother had 16 children, and her mother had 14 and raised 9. As a child, Elizabeth’s father worked at an alkali salt plant. Elizabeth learned to quilt from her mother and says, “I just felt I needed to make them.” Growing up, Elizabeth’s family used to sleep under cotton blankets and quilts with one feather bed under you and another on top during the winter.</p>
            
            <p>Over the years, Elizabeth made a lot of quilts. She remembers making a friendship quilt out of all of her friend’s dresses. Most of Elizabeth’s quilts are made from old sheeting or old clothes, with cotton blankets as batting. She gets a lot of quilt ideas from her mother, and often makes two quilts and two quilt tops a year. Elizabeth used to quilt mostly in winter because she was busy all summer canning and working with her husband on their farm. 
        </p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Anita Gilmore - 1905</title>
        <anchor>10</anchor>
        <type>home</type>
        <patterns>tags: nine diamonds, churn dasher, bow tie, crazy quilt</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>Anita was born in 1905 and married in 1926. She remembers that her grandparents had straw tick mattresses and featherbeds. Anita learned to quilt from her mother and got ideas for quilts out of magazines and from friends. She says that, in her day, quilts were never made from white fabric because it dirties too easily. </p>
                
             <p>   Anita believes that now people are more concerned with how the quilts look--when she first started quilting she was more concerned with having covers for the bed. She made 3-4 quilts a year for much of her life. She also always made quilts for people whose houses had burned down and for her nephew.</p>
                
               <p> At the time of the interview (in the 1970s), Anita and women from her church were constructing a quilt to raffle off as an effort to raise money to fight the Appalachian Power Company’s controversial proposal to construct a hydroelectric power plant (which would’ve had a negative net energy yield) on the New River, thereby damming it and flooding much existing farm land.</p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Deb Simon - 1902</title>
        <anchor>11</anchor>
        <type>home</type>
        <patterns>nine diamonds, dresden plate, flower garden, irish chain, pineapple</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>Deb has two quilts, one hand woven blanket, and two coverlets that she inherited from her grandmother. Deb learned to quilt from her mother; she can remember her mother teaching her to cut the pieces for a nine diamond quilt and the process of tacking it together. Deb’s mother believed that using a sewing machine to piece or quilt lowered the value of the finished quilt “a whole lot.” Later, Deb got ideas for quilts from neighbors or from her family members. She remembers that "some of the poorer families would make quilts from old clothes, but none of my family ever did.”</p>
                
               <p> Deb recalls an aunt who made a crazy quilt and could remember where each piece in the top came from; many of her neighbors had contributed pieces of dress scraps to the quilt. She believes that women “just made [quilts], a lot of times, because they liked to make beautiful things.” Deb’s children only had hand woven blankets and quilts to sleep under as they grew up. </p>
                
               <p> Deb married 1923. Her husband’s mother died before they were married, but he found an old trunk that had a half dozen comforters and a few quilts put away with his initials embroidered into them, so he knew they were for him.</p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Lucy Simmons - 1901</title>
        <anchor>12</anchor>
        <type>love</type>
        <patterns>trip around the world, old home, lone star, nine diamonds, string quilt, tulip quilt, nine diamonds, crazy quilt</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>Lucy Simmons was born in 1901. Her father was a brick mason and also had a farm, where she grew up. As a child, Lucy and her sister slept together in the same bed, and thus needed extra large quilts. She recalls that, "Our beds was the most particular things that we had at home,” and that she was never allowed to play or sit in bed during the day.</p>
                
                <p>Lucy made her first quilt, a nine diamond, when she was 18.  She recalls that her grandmother made one or two quilts every month in the winter, or about five each year. Her grandmother also used to make very heavy crazy quilts from old coats. </p>
                
              <p>  To Lucy’s grandmother and mother, quilts were a treasured gift. She says, ”If they wanted to give the nicest present that they could think of to somebody that was very dear to them, it would have been a quilt. Just like you would like to give a nice present to your best friend, whoever it would be.” Quilts were a gift symbolic of love and closeness Lucy recovers a time that her mother also gave a quilt to a neighbor whose house had burned down.</p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Betty Graham - 1915</title>
        <anchor>13</anchor>
        <type>family</type>
        <patterns>pine tree, wedding ring, nine diamonds, strip quilt,</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>Betty was born in 1915 and was the oldest of six children. Her maternal grandmother was an American Indian who made many quilts “just to keep warm—not for show.” Betty’s mother taught her to piece quilts when she was ten.</p>
                
                <p>Betty remembers quilting with her mother throughout her childhood. She remembers that her family would collect catalogues with samples of men’s suit fabric in them, then tear out these small samples and save them to make quilts, which would be filled with wool from their own sheep. Betty’s mother also used to buy bags of fabric remnants for piecing.</p>
                
               <p> Betty remembers attending quiltings and bean hulling events with her mother. Aside from working at these events, neighbors would also chat and swap recipes. Betty says that, if someone’s house burned down, a quilting bee might be held to piece and quilt for the victim.</p>
                
              <p>  Betty was married in 1930 and continued to make quilts. When her oldest daughter was married, Betty thought it would be nice to make her a quilt to begin her household, so she hand pieced a wedding ring quilt as a special gift.</p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Joan Fisher - 1914</title>
        <anchor>14</anchor>
        <type>marriage</type>
        <patterns>star quilt, double cross, crazy quilt, frog quilt, trip around the world, spool quilt, josephs coat, odd feller, endless chain, fan quilt, broken dish</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>Growing up, Joan’s Father worked in the boiler room of a lumber company and then in the mines. In his later years, he came home to farm the family’s land. Joan’s mother wove beautiful “counterpane” bedspreads and blankets and made quilts. As a child, Joan learned to spin and card wool for her mother to use in weaving. Joan’s mother made each of her grandchildren a quilt when the graduated from high school, and also pieced a quilt top for Jane, but she died before she was able to quilt it. Jane inherited the unfinished top, and also the desire to make quilts as special gifts for close friends.</p>
                
               <p> Joan remember participating in many quilting bees. A quilting bee might take all day (from 10 a.m. until dark), with everyone gathered around a quilting frame propped on chairs or hung from the ceiling. These events also included a lot of food. Joan says that whenever the church got a new preacher, she and her friends would make him a quilt with his name embroidered in it. They wanted to “make him something he could use.”</p>
                
              <p>  Joan was married in 1930 at the age of 16. Joan admits that she married young, and she advises other young girls to “get something out of life” before you marry.</p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Myra Prescott - 1920</title>
        <anchor>15</anchor>
        <type>craft</type>
        <patterns>flower garden, wedding ring</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>Myra became interested in quilts after watching her mother and mother-in-law. She says "My mother in law did right much piecing of quilts, and of course I got more interested and more interested in it. Then I just decided if everyone else could quilt, why couldn't I?”</p>
                
                <p>Myra’s mother had always machine-pieced beautiful quilts from scraps of dresses she’d made for herself or for her daughters. When Myra first began to notice quilts and think about making them, her mother was making wedding ring pattern quilts. For Christmas, Myra’s mother often gave her quilts that she could “go ahead and wash and use.”</p>
                
              <p>  Myra learned to quilt simply by watching others quilt. It was difficult at first because she had young children to take care of, but she already knew how to knit and crochet, and so she knew that, “I could, if I wanted to, do almost anything. I don't let anything bluff me, as long as it's for me. If I mess up something, it's all right, long as it's mine." For Myra, making mistakes didn't matter, as long as she was making products she would keep anyway.
            </p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Kenny Jones - 1918</title>
        <anchor>16</anchor>
        <type>family</type>
        <patterns>log cabin, irish chain, rocky mountain star, lone star, nine diamonds, trip around the world, bow tie, maple leaf</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>Growing up, Kenny’s mother sewed for all 11 of her children. He remembers that she would sometimes send himself and his siblings to pick wool off of sheep that had died on an adjacent farm, then spin that wool and use it to knit socks. In addition, his mother also worked in the garden, raised chickens and turkeys, milked cows, and made quilts. </p>
                
                <p>Kenny remembers that sometimes neighbors would come help his mother quilt. According to Kenny, one or two women might come over to help, stay and talk, then eat dinner. He says that they often talked about “their gardens and about their children, and about their sewing and how many beans they put up and how they pickled them and how they made krout and how they dried apples and all such as that… how much butter they had sold that week or month, and how many eggs.” </p>
                
              <p>  Kenny learned to sew and quilt from his mother. He began to make quilts to sell after staying with a friend who noticed his sewing skills and asked him to quilt seven pieced tops. Now he makes lots of quilts to sell to help pay his medical bills. Sometimes he also gives quilts away to “good people,” like the woman who took care of his mother in old age.
            </p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Jennifer Willis - 1904</title>
        <anchor>17</anchor>
        <type>craft</type>
        <patterns>nine diamonds, lone star, dresden plate, flower garden, double wedding ring, friendship quilt</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>Although both of Jennifer’s mother and bother of her grandmothers quilted, Jennifer did not develop an interesting in learning to quilt herself until she saw quilt patterns in a home magazine and decided it would be a good winter project. Jennifer taught herself to piece on the machine and made about two quilts a year though much of her life. </p>
                
                <p>Jennifer always bought new fabric to make her quilts, be she remembers that her mother and grandmothers used scraps in theirs. She says that her maternal grandmother would only have made quilts in winter because she would be busy during the summer working in her garden, milking her cow, and churning butter. Jennifer’s family was all farmers who grew corn, tobacco, wheat and oats, although she notes that “there was a lot you had to buy that you can’t raise” like sugar and coffee.</p>
                
                <p>Jennifer often helped make quilts that her church sells to raise money. She says that eight women will gather and quilt and entire quilt in together.</p>
                
                <p>When Jennifer’s children got married, she gave each of them a quilt that they had previously professed admiration for because “that would be something they could remember me by.”
            </p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    <story>
        <title>Josephine Duncan - 1918</title>
        <anchor>18</anchor>
        <type>craft</type>
        <patterns>crazy quilts, flower garden, sunflower, bow tie</patterns>
        <description>
            <p>Josephine’s mother was an Extension Homemakers Club agent who grew up helping to weave woolen blankets, quilting, and making braided rugs. Her mother believed that keeping kids busy kept them out of trouble and taught Josephine to quilt. When Josephine and each of her sisters were married, her mother made a quilt as a wedding gift. </p>
                
               <p> Josephine remembers attending lots of quilting bees, as a child and as an adult. She notes that whenever her church got a new pastor, some women would make him a quilt. The quilting parties Josephine goes to today are not different than the ones she remembers attending as a child. They are still just about seeing your neighbors and talking.  Josephine says that at quilting parties the hostess prepared dinner and "you cooked up everything you had.”
            </p>
        </description>
    </story>
    
    
</quilts>